Welcome, everyone to CS 336,
Language Models from Scratch.
This is the teaching staff.
I'm Percy.
This is Tatsu, Marcel,
Herman and Steven,
and we're bringing you
the third edition of 336.
So we'll just do a quick
round of introductions.
So I'd like to say that
I've been doing language
models for 20 years,
but most of that time
was small language models.
Actually, this is still small
in the grand scheme of things.
I think when Tatsu and I
started teaching this class two
years ago, we
weren't really sure
what we were going to expect,
but we were very pleasantly
surprised that so
many people wanted
to learn how to build language
models from scratch, especially
in these days when a
coding agent could probably
zero shot a language model.
I'm really glad
to see all of you
here to actually want
to learn how they work.
Yeah, thanks.
I'm Tatsu, I'm one of
the co-instructors.
I'll be talking
to you once we get
to architectures and scaling and
all these other very fun things.
I'm really excited.
This is the most fun class
I've taught in my time here.
I think every year,
Percy makes fun of me
because he says you have to redo
all your lectures because you
took on architectures, and
everything changes every time.
But it's actually pretty
fun for me to do it.
And it's the first time that
I've had that experience.
So I'm looking forward to going
through this experience again
with you all.
Hello, I'm Marcel.
I've seen this
class once before,
and I'm returning because it
was so much fun last time.
[LAUGHTER]
It's a lot of work though.
In my research, I do
architecture stuff,
I do higher order gradients,
and I do training.
Yeah, looking forward to
working with you guys.
Hello, everyone, I'm Herman.
A year ago, I didn't really how
LLMs worked, so I think for me,
tokens were the things you
collect in video games,
and attention was the thing you
had, like the attention economy.
Then after spending a lot of
time on this course last year,
I'm now doing LLM research,
and I'm really excited to TA
this year.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Stephen.
I am a first time
CA for this course
and I'm very excited about it.
I think it will be a lot of fun.
Broadly, in my research, I
work on language models, theory
and some data efficiency stuff,
and I'm excited to meet you all.
All right, so let's
go into things.
So this is the third
time we're offering it.
Last year, we decided to put
all our lectures on YouTube.
So some of you have seen it.
So what's new?
Well, what hasn't changed is
'from scratch' philosophy.
We still believe strongly
that by building everything
from the ground up, you really
learn how everything works.
Of course, we don't actually
build everything up from scratch
because that wouldn't
fit in the quarter.
So over the last two years,
we've been refining our recipe
and figuring out what are
the things that you build up
from scratch that are
the most high value?
And then finally, as Tatsu
alluded to, even in a year,
a lot has changed.
I think this year we're going
to spend maybe a bit more time
on mixture of experts.
And of course, agents are
very popular these days.
So getting a handle
on long-context
and what is needed for that
are going to be important.
So why did we make this course?
And I think the
problem two years ago
was that researchers were
becoming disconnected
from the underlying technology.
It used to be the
case may 10 years ago,
all AI researchers would
just implement and train
their own models.
And then even eight
years ago, people
would download pre-trained
models such as Bert
and fine tune them.
And I think a lot of
today, you can get by
by simply prompting a model.
And of course, there's nothing
wrong with prompting model.
I think you can do
amazing things with it.
I think moving up the
abstraction in general
is a great thing, but
abstractions are leaky,
and sometimes, I'm sure all
of you have prompted models,
you run into situations
where something is--
you wanted to do something,
but it just can't do it
and there's no recourse.
And I would argue that if
you're really interested
in fundamental research, by
simply prompting a model,
you're vastly constraining
the set of options, the design
space you're looking at.
And by looking at
fundamental research,
you really need to tear
up the whole stack.
So I would argue that
full understanding of how
language models work
is really necessary
for fundamental research.
And the way that we're going
to get an understanding
is by building.
That's the philosophy
of the class.
But there's one
small problem, which
is that industrialization of
language models has happened.
Frontier models are
really, really expensive.
Even, this is three years ago.
GPT-4 was supposedly costing
$100 million to train,
and now costs probably are
on the order of $1 billion,
although that's speculative.
And the number of GPUs that
all the big labs are building
is just immense.
Furthermore, there's no details
on how any of these models
are built. So even back in
2023, the GPT-4 paper explicitly
says that due to a competitive
landscape and safety
implications, we're not going
to share anything about how
the models are being built.
So these frontier
models are in some sense
out of the reach for us.
Now, we could build
small language models,
and we will build
language models.
But I think it's important to
remember that these might not
be representative of the
actual frontier models.
And I'll give you two examples
why this might be the case.
So here's one.
This is from actually
quite a long time ago.
I think back in 2021.
If we're going to
spend more time on flop
counting and looking at where
the compute is being spent.
But if you look at small
scales, the fraction
of flops spent in the
MLP layers is around 44%.
And if you scale up to
175B, then it goes to 80%.
So what you optimize and
what matters at large scale
is going to be different
from small scale.
So if you did a bunch
of small scale stuff
here on the attention, you might
not experience the same benefits
at large scale.
The second example is that we
know of emergence of behavior
with scale.
So small models, this is, again,
for a while ago, but even back
then, if you have a
0 shot or a few shot
learning of various
tasks, it basically,
seemed like nothing
was working, and only
when you reach a critical
scale do you suddenly
see a lot of improvement.
So again, if you're
working on small scale,
you might not see certain
types of phenomenon
compared to if you were
working at full scale.
OK, so that might be a little
bit disheartening, but fear not,
we're going to learn
something in this class.
And the question is, what can we
learn that actually transfers?
And I think it's important
to break this down
into three types of knowledge.
First, there's the
mechanics of how
things work, what a transformer
is, how model parallelism works.
There's mindset,
which is, how do you
go about approaching
building a language model?
We're going to talk about how
you want to squeeze the most out
of your hardware, taking
scaling seriously.
And then finally, intuitions.
Which data modeling
decisions are going
to yield good performance?
So now, in this
class, I think we
can do a pretty
good job of teaching
the mechanics, which is how
things work and the mindset.
And we're going to really
emphasize that you profile
and benchmark everything and
try to optimize for efficiency.
These things do transfer
to a larger scale.
Now, the intuitions about
what modeling decisions
and what data decisions do
work might not necessarily
transfer across scales.
For that, you actually
have to go somewhere where
you can do things at scale.
So on the note of
intuitions, it is
worth remarking that some
design decisions are just
not justifiable, and just purely
come from experimentation.
Whereas mechanics, you
can, by construction,
see how the parallelism
and how kernels are going
to speed things up and so on.
But for intuitions about
what modeling changes work,
I think you just have
to run experiments.
There's this famous
Noam Shazeer paper
that introduces the
SwiGLU activation, which
we're going to look about.
And in the conclusion
section, he very honestly
has this final sentence which
says, we offer no explanation.
We attribute their success, of
these architectures, all else,
to divine benevolence.
So that, in some sense,
is something that you just
have to gain from experience.
Final note about the bitter
lesson, which I think
has been circulating and
people talk about it.
I think there's a common
misconception here,
what it means.
I think the wrong
interpretation is
that scale is all that matters.
Algorithms don't matter.
But that's not correct.
The right interpretation is
that algorithms that scale are
what that-- or what matters.
And you can think
about very simply
that the accuracy of your model
is basically your efficiency
times the resources.
So efficiency is
output over input,
and resources is the input.
And efficiency is
actually, in some sense,
way more important at
larger scale, right?
If you're doing a
small scale experiment,
if your run takes twice
as long, maybe you just
wait twice as long and
then you come back later.
But if you're doing
things at scale,
that could be hundreds
of millions of dollars.
And you definitely
don't want to do that.
Even like a 5% improvement
might be a big deal.
So in fact, efficiency
is actually really,
really critical.
And I hope to bake
that into your mindset
as one of the consequences
of this class.
And empirically, if you look
at-- there's this paper from
OpenAI in 2020 that showed
there's a 44x algorithmic
efficiency on ImageNet
between 2012 and 2019.
And it's surely the case that
hardware did get a lot better,
but that also comes with
algorithmic improvements.
And of course, when you
multiply them together,
that's when you see a huge bump
in efficiency and accuracy.
So the framing
with all that said
is, what is the best model one
can build with a certain data
and compute budget?
For pre-training,
it's mostly, we're
going to talk about
compute budget,
because we're going to assume
that we have a lot more data
than we have compute.
But if you're in a setting
where you're data limited
or you have stashed away,
actually, tons of B200s,
then you might be data bound.
So in other words,
maximize efficiency.
And we're going to
see this theme come up
throughout the class.
OK.
So next, I want to spend a bit
of time talking about language
models and a bit of a history
and just contextualization
before we jump into the
more technical details.
So language models have
been around for a while.
Shannon, back in the '50s was
using language models to measure
the entropy of English.
And for a long
time, N-gram models
were used, actually, in
machine translation and speech
recognition systems.
And they weren't
the whole system,
but they were an important
part of making sure
that you generated fluent text.
I would say that the lineage
of the Modern Language models
comes from neural architectures.
And so there is a bunch
of ideas, I think,
which are important
to this development.
So in the '90s, there was LSTMs.
Yoshua Bengio, actually, wrote
the first neural language model
in paperback in 2003.
This is actually not an LSTM.
This was just a
feedforward network that
looked at the small context.
And then there was a Seq2Seq
modeling, which boldly said,
we can actually compress a
whole sentence into a vector.
The atom optimizer
attention mechanism,
which was developed for
machine translation.
The transformer architecture,
which built on top
of that, which
was also developed
for machine translation.
And then scaling up to a mixture
of experts model parallelism.
You see a lot of different
architecture and also systems
and optimizer ideas
developed in the 2010s.
And then by the
late 2010s, I think,
things were starting to
get really interesting.
So there was the ELMo and BERT.
These are language models that
were trained on lots of text,
and then you could
fine tune them
on some downstream tasks
like question answering,
and it would show a huge
improvement on that.
So the model there was, take
one of these models and then
fine tune.
And then Google had a
paper that was really,
I think, foreshadowing this
view of prompt in, response out.
So it was really,
I think, OpenAI
that really opened
up the floodgates
here by embracing scaling.
So they had GPT paper back
in, I think, 2018 or so.
They scaled it up to GPT-2, and
then they really figured out
or embrace the idea
of scaling laws,
which we're going to
talk about in a second,
which enable them
to train GPT-3,
which was a much more
massive, almost more than 10x,
the largest model at the time.
And it could show
emergent behavior
like in-context learning.
At that point, Google
was saying, OK,
we need to do something too.
So they trained a massive model.
It turned out to
be undertrained.
And it turned out that their
DeepMind, which was not
integrated with
Google at the time,
had figured out optimal-compute,
optimal scaling laws.
So all of this was happening.
And after GPT-3 came out,
I think for many folks,
this was kind of a wake up call.
And at that time, there were
a lot of early attempts to,
let's try to replicate this.
So there was a
grassroots organization
called Eleuther that created
some open data sets and models.
They weren't very large because
they didn't have much compute.
Meta first LLM, you could
tell that it's a replication
because it was like
175 billion parameters,
but it was not a
very good model.
They ran into a lot
of hardware issues.
And then there was another,
Hugging Face BigScience project.
So these models were, I
would say, not very strong.
Then in the last three years, I
think, the open model ecosystem
has changed quite
a bit, with Meta
kind of leading the way with
the Llama series of models.
Llama, Llama 2, Llama 3.
Mistral got in the game.
And then a whole set
of Chinese models.
I think I'm missing some.
Like, ByteDance has something,
and I think Tencent probably
has some other stuff.
So it's hard to keep
track of everything,
but everyone's heard
of DeepSeek and Qwen.
So I think I got the main ones.
But I think what's interesting
and exciting about these is now
we have open weight models that
are approaching closed models.
So depending on who you
ask and how you benchmark,
they might be a little
bit behind or comparable.
But they are definitely
very, very credible models
that are being widely
used in industry.
Now there's another
line of work,
which is going beyond just
releasing open weight models.
AI2, NVIDIA and the Marin
project, which I work on,
we try to provide not just
the weights, but the paper
and the code and
the data so that we
can understand how
these models are
built in a more thorough way.
Why do I emphasize this
open ecosystem so much?
Mostly because this course
would not be possible,
I think, without these
models by the fact
that there are still
many papers that
are being published about
how these big MOEs and RL
systems are working enables
us to at least glimpse
into how these frontier
models are being built,
and trying to
triangulate the pieces.
Now, I think, of course,
a lot of the details,
even with these Qwen
papers, I think they're
missing a lot of details.
So can't reproduce them.
Notably, the data mixture is
something that we don't, but I
think it's much
better than nothing.
OK.
So in the last decade,
I think, the idea
of what a language model
has changed, right?
It used to be something
that you fine-tuned,
and then it was
something you prompt.
And now in the ChatGPT era,
it was something you talked to
and that you can have
a conversation with.
And now-- OK, I guess
I don't have internet.
[CHUCKLING]
That's fine.
And now, we're in
the era of agents.
If you click on this
link, it basically
shows you a giant agent trace.
And I'm still-- it's
mind boggling how strong
some of these models are.
You give it like a
page of text and it
does some really complicated
agentic coding task.
So what we demand of our
language models today
is probably beyond the
imagination of any one back
10 years ago.
That said, I think the
fundamentals, I think,
haven't changed that much.
Largely, we still built
on GPUs and kernels.
We still optimize using
gradient or stochastic
gradient-like approaches.
We still have the
transformer in attention,
And we'll talk a little bit
more about architectures,
but it hasn't changed that much.
I think the specs are different.
Now we demand greater
context lengths,
which means that inference
efficiency matters even more.
So the good news
for us is that we
didn't have to completely
change this class.
Only Tatsu's section on the
latest Chinese architectures.
[LAUGHTER]
But the fundamentals,
I think, are here
to stay, at least for now.
OK, maybe I'll pause
there in case there's
any questions or thoughts.
OK.
So let's go on.
So a brief interlude.
So what is this program?
So this is what I call
a executable lecture.
If you think it looks
like a Python program,
it is because it is
actually a Python program,
but it has been rendered
for your viewing pleasure.
So when I step through it as
actually executing the lecture.
And it makes us possible
to basically step
through code, which
will be, hopefully,
interesting and important later.
And you can also see the
hierarchical structure
of this lecture.
For example, we're done
with this function.
Now, we go back to main.
OK, so let's talk about
the course logistics,
and the syllabus,
which I think is going
to take a good chunk of time.
So all the information
is online at this website
or cs336.stanford.edu.
This is a 5-unit class.
I think this, probably, class
has a certain reputation,
so I don't need to belabor the
point too much, but this is--
we have five assignments.
They are pretty intense.
Even the first assignment
according to this one.
Review was actually equivalent
to the 5 assignments.
First, CS 224n.
I've been told, also, this
is exaggerated, but better
to, I guess, be conservative
in your estimates.
So why should you-- so why
should you take this course OK,
so first you have
an obsessive need me
to understand how things work.
That should be your
primary objective.
I think just pure curiosity
on how language models work.
And then in doing
the class, you'll
develop a much stronger
research, engineering muscles
and have the confidence
to go into a new setting
and be equipped to deal with
whatever situation comes up.
So I think when I
started at Stanford,
I created this class
called Statistical Learning
Theory, which was, basically,
teaching the theoretical side
of machine learning.
And that was nice because
it equipped people.
So when you read a paper, you
can understand all the math.
And now, since the
field has shifted
a lot more towards this more
systems and empirical side
of things, this is the kind
of analogous class, which
gives people enough depth
that they feel that everything
else seems kind of easy.
So why should you
not take this course?
This is important
because there's reasons
you shouldn't take this course.
First, you actually want to get
some research done this quarter.
You should probably
talk to your advisor.
They should know you're
taking this course.
Otherwise, there'll
be-- probably,
there might be some surprises.
You're interested in
learning the hottest
new techniques in AI.
I think there are many other
great courses, seminar courses,
topics courses that
are good for that.
We don't do many of the things.
We don't do multimodality.
We don't talk about
agents in any depth.
So if you want to
learn about that stuff,
this is not the right
course for that.
If you come in and say, I
have an application domain,
I want to get good
results on it,
probably this is not the right
course, at least to start.
I always recommend just prompt
a model, fine tune a model.
And then as a last resort,
you pre-train your own model.
Because it is a pain
and it's also expensive,
but it's a lot of fun.
OK.
So if you are not
taking the class,
you can self-follow
along at home.
So all the lecture materials
will be posted on the website.
Oops!
And they are also
recorded through CGOE.
So thank you, CGOE,
for doing that.
And later, they will be
published to YouTube.
Now, of course, following at
home and watching the lectures
is great, but you learn, really,
by doing the assignments.
So you'll have to figure out how
to motivate yourself to do that.
OK, so speaking of assignments,
we have five assignments.
The philosophy assignment is,
how do we do from scratch,
but not just, say,
build a language model,
and that's the assignment?
So we don't provide
scaffolding code,
but we do provide a
bunch of unit tests
to make sure that
whatever you're building
is actually correct,
so that you don't
get this sparse reward setting
where you submit a homework
and it's either correct or not.
What I recommend
is that you can--
the assignments are structured
so that much of the assignment
can actually be done
locally on your laptop.
You can implement it and
check for correctness.
And then we are
providing a cluster
so that you can do an
actual training run
to see what the accuracy
is, or get a bunch of GPUs
to actually benchmark the
performance of some kernel.
And then for fun,
we will have, some
leaderboards for most of
the assignments, at least.
And they will look
something like, well, now
that you've learned
about this topic,
I'll try to minimize
the perplexities given
some of budget.
And both Marcel and Herman
were masters of leaderboards
back in the day, which was
last year, or the year before.
So if you want tips on that,
I'm sure they would be happy--
actually, I don't know, if they
would tell you their secrets,
but you can try.
OK, so last year, we were
thinking about, well,
what can AI do?
It was like, OK, well,
I mean, yes, everyone
can use AI, but just
try to do your best.
I think now, I
think, coding agents
have gotten so good that
they can just all solve
all the assignments, right?
But to state the obvious,
obviously, you're
not going to learn anything
if you just feed in the PDF
Assignment 1 into a Cloud Code.
At the same time, AI can be very
useful for answering questions
and tutoring.
So we have to find a
way to leverage AI.
So what we've decided to do is,
we provide you a AGENTS.md file,
or equivalently, a prompt which
asks the AI to be pedagogically
minded.
You can read more about
it in our AI policy guide.
And the requirement is that
if you're going to use AI,
use it with this prompt.
And so it will answer
questions about code,
it will clarify
any understanding,
but it won't accidentally
generate the transformer for you
when the homework is to
implement the transformer.
And this is the first year
we're trying to do this,
so please try it out
and give us feedback
if it's working or not working.
So compute.
So this year we have--
thanks to Modal,
they have provided us
with compute credits
on their platform.
It's actually quite nice.
You can get a number of--
unlike last year--
well, I guess, you guys
didn't take the class last year.
Last year, we had a
cluster you SSH into.
This is using more
of an API to--
which I was initially skeptical
of, but looking at it,
actually, is pretty
pleasant to use.
So again, try it out and give
us feedback on how it is.
We've written a guide on how
to access and use the compute.
OK, any questions
about course logistics?
OK.
All right, let's
talk about what we're
going to cover in this class.
So there's, basically,
five parts mirroring
the five assignments
that you'll have.
Basic system, scaling,
laws, data, and alignment.
So I'm going to now
go through each part
and just give you a taste
of what you will learn.
So in the basics, this is
basically the first two weeks.
The goal is to just be able
to train a language model
and build it from scratch.
So the components
here are, we're
going to tokenize
the data, we're
going to define
architecture, and then
we're going to implement
optimizer and train it.
So then you wonder, what are
the rest of the classes for?
Well, we'll get to there.
So let's start
with tokenization.
The tokenization
is really about,
what are the atoms that
the model operates on?
And formally, a
tokenizer converts
between raw inputs,
which are just bytes,
and a sequence of integers,
which represent the tokens.
Conceptually, it's a
segmentation of the text.
We're going to talk about
the Byte-Pair Encoding,
BPE tokenizer,
which intuitively,
breaks the input into
frequently occurring chunks.
And then remember, this class
is about maximizing efficiency,
so through an efficiency
lens, tokenization is good
because it takes
a long sequence,
if you just think about
the raw byte stream,
and reduces it into a
smaller number of tokens.
But more subtly, but
maybe more importantly,
it allows you to do
adaptive computation.
So maybe some places are
actually a lot of bites,
but actually, it should be
compressed into a one token,
whereas some of the more rare
or interesting parts of input
should be left as
multiple tokens.
OK, we'll talk more about this.
I just want to mention
that every year,
I'm hoping that I don't
have to teach tokenization,
because the dream is to really
have an end-to-end way that
directly operates on bytes.
And there's been a number
of work, including recently,
there's been these networks
that seems promising,
but so far, these have not
been scaled to the frontier.
And since the frontier models
are still using tokenizers,
we felt like it would be still
wise to teach tokenizers.
OK, so now after you
tokenize your input,
you have a bunch of tokens.
Now you define a model on top.
And everyone, I think,
has a familiarity
with the transformer.
And if you've taken
224n, the MLP class,
then you've seen transformers.
Since then, I think, there
have been a lot of improvements
or refinements to transformers,
which I think are important.
And Tatsu is going to talk
more about this in a bit.
But just to run through
a set of types of things
that one might have
to think about,
so the activation
functions have evolved.
How do you do positional
encodings has evolved.
How you normalize has
the different layers.
Blow up has evolved.
Instead of doing full
attention, there's
many ways to basically reduce
the attention computation,
because attention is
n squared and where
n is a sequence length, and
that gets really expensive.
So there's a bunch
of ideas around that.
If you're more
ambitious, you can
look at these state-space models
or equivalently linear attention
like Mamba and Gated DeltaNet.
These have become more
popular in the last few years.
And usually, some hybrid between
these models and attention
seems to work quite well.
So, we'll be exploring
some of that.
And then within the MLP
layers of the transformer,
the original transformer
was just a dense MLP,
and now a mixture of experts
has become the dominant paradigm
for building compute
efficient transformers.
So we're going to
talk about that.
And of course with a
mixture of experts,
it's not just
defining architecture,
but we'll see that we'll also
need different techniques
for training the model.
And then finally, perhaps
somewhat boringly,
but an important
question is, what is
the shape of your transformer?
How many layers?
How many heads?
What is hidden dimension?
Number of experts?
This might come in more as
we talk about scaling laws,
but setting these is actually--
seems kind of almost trivial.
It's a hyperparameter, but
actually in the context
of scaling and language models,
it has a huge, huge implication.
So once you define your
model architecture,
how do you train the model?
And here there's a bunch of
design decisions around the loss
function.
There's next token prediction,
which is the default.
But people have found that
predicting more than one token
seems to be helpful for
improving the model.
And there's optimizers.
People used to use AdamW,
but increasingly, Muon
has been used, especially with
some of the latest open models,
such as the Kimi K2 models.
Initialization, which,
again, sounds kind of boring,
but turns out to
have a huge impact
on how your ability
in the training
stability of larger models.
Learning rate schedule.
Regularization.
Batch size.
And then MoE specific things.
So you look at this list
and you might think, well,
these are just hyperparameters.
I'm going to try a bunch
of different options out.
But it turns out that really
being very careful about setting
these hyperparameters
in a principled way
will make the difference between
a run that just blows up and is
useless between a run that is
achieving state of the art.
OK, I'll come back to that point
when we talk about scaling loss.
So then in Assignment 1,
what you're going to do
is you're going to
implement the BPE tokenizer,
implement the transformer, the
loss function, the optimizer,
the whole training step.
We're going to make you do a
bunch of resource accounting
so you understand where
your flops are going.
You're going to
train some models
on these data sets like
TinyStories and OpenWebText.
And then there's going
to be a leaderboard where
you're going to try to
drive down perplexity
as fast as you can.
So for those of you familiar
with NanoGPT, speedruns,
it's kind of similar to that.
OK, so by the end
of Assignment 1,
you should be able to walk
away and build a language
model from scratch.
So that's very exciting.
If I have a high
level takeaway here,
it's that while the tokenizer
and modeling and training
are presented as distinct
pieces, it is actually,
everything is about
balancing the following.
So you want expressive
models because you
want to represent the
complexities of the data,
but at the same time, you want
your training to be stable.
And we're going to talk
a lot about how do you
keep the parameter and gradient
norms in this goldilocks zone
so they don't blow
up and don't vanish.
Turns out, a lot of
training language models
is about just stability.
And then finally, efficiency,
which is somewhat more
straightforward.
You just make it run
fast on hardware.
But you're going to see
interesting things like,
if we change the architecture,
a lot of the architecture
decisions are, well, we can
make it faster by, let's say,
reducing the projecting of
a low dimensional space.
But then the question
is, does it work as well?
And so making those trade
offs is something that--
is the name of the game here.
So in Assignment 2, we're
going to dive more deeply
into systems.
And the goal here is just to
get most out of your hardware.
So we're going to
talk about kernels,
how you parallelize
across multiple GPUs,
and how you do inference.
So the basics,
which we're actually
going to start on next lecture,
I mentioned resource accounting,
and I think you've all
probably built models before.
But this is really about keeping
track of where all the flops go
and where all the
memory is being spent.
So we're going to spend
some time, basically,
doing the resource accounting.
We're going to see this
formula that comes up,
how many flops does
training SMDB on model
on 1 trillion tokens?
Well, it's six times
n times D roughly.
And where does that come from?
And then we're going to
look at the hardware.
And here's a cartoon
I picture of what
to remark about hardware,
is that, your memory is not
where your compute
is, and you have
to move either your parameters
or activations from the memory
to compute, do the
compute, and move it back.
And that often is
the bottleneck.
So for example, B200, which
we'll have the opportunity
to play with, it has 2.25
petaFLOPS per second if bf16.
And has 8 terabytes
second of memory.
So what does that mean?
I think when we--
I think I'll do
this next lecture.
We're going to break this
down and use this information
to do some calculations
and see how
long different types of
algorithms will need to take.
We're going to talk about
roofline analysis, which
allows us to understand whether
a computation is bottlenecked
by either a compute or memory.
In general, it is memory.
And then talk a little bit about
benchmarking and profiling.
So here's what a
DGX B200 looks like.
You have 8 GPUs.
They're connected via MV link.
And then if you have many--
if you have a thousand GPUs,
then you would have
multiple of these
and they're connected either
InfiniBand or ethernet.
So the next two parts when we
talk about system is kernel.
So a kernel is basically a
function that runs on the GPU.
And when you're just
using plain PyTorch,
all the PyTorch
primitives actually
correspond to launching
particular kernels, which
are built in.
So you're already using
kernels, whether you it or not.
But the point is that, for
certain types of computation,
if you look at it, you can
actually write custom kernels
to make the GPUs go faster.
And the main principle here
is organizing the compute
to minimize data movement.
So remember, this picture moving
data from memory is expensive.
So you want to try
to minimize that.
So just as a simple
example, suppose
you wanted to compute
A and B. So often,
you would have to read from
your high bandwidth memory, HBM,
compute it, write it
back, and then read again,
compute it, write it back.
So then, you're basically
sending the data back and forth
twice.
And there's this idea called
fusion, where you read it once,
do both of the computations,
and you write it back.
And that will save
you a lot of time.
So that's operator fusion.
Tiling is a more sophisticated
variant around the same idea.
There's also-- GPUs have also
gotten a lot more complicated.
And I'm not sure how
many of these details
we'll have time to get
into, but at least we
want to expose you to some of
the peculiarities, I would say,
of GPUs and give you an
appreciation for the types
of things that one has
to consider in order
to squeeze as much juice
out of them as possible.
And we'll write some
kernels in and Triton.
So what happens if you
have thousands of GPUs?
So the principle of minimized
data movement is still the same.
The only thing is that moving
data between different GPUs
is even more expensive.
We're going to talk about how
these very classic collective
operations, gather and
reduce and all-reduce
are the way to think about,
basically, distributed training.
The general game is that we
have these model parameters,
We have activations, gradients
and optimizer states,
and they need to be sharded
or split across multiple GPUs.
And of course, you need
to bring the right data
to the right nodes to make
the compute and write it back.
So there's a whole
kind of orchestration,
and how to do that
efficiently is going
to be the topic of this unit.
And there's multiple
ways to shard.
You can shard by
splitting up your data,
splitting up your model,
splitting up different layers
in the model, splitting
up the sequences,
splitting up between experts.
And we'll talk
about the trade offs
that come with each of these.
OK.
And then finally, we're going
to talk about inference.
Which, as I mentioned,
is growing in importance.
So the goal of inference is
to actually use the model.
So minor detail here.
So inference is, of course,
you need to use inference
when you're chatting
with a model,
but it also is useful for
reinforcement learning.
It's useful for
doing the rollouts.
Test-time compute, generating
synthetic data, evaluation.
So inference is a
very critical part
of what it means to do
language modeling work.
So we're probably not
going to spend as much time
as I like on this because the
course is already kind of filled
up, but we'll see
what we can do.
There was some discussion
around whether we
should make you write inference
from scratch, but we'll see.
So the way to think
about inference
is that there's two phases,
a prefill and a decode.
In the prefill,
You take the prompt
and then you feed all
the tokens forward
and build key value pairs.
This is very much like
what happens in training.
And then in the
decoding part, tokens
are generated one at a time.
And this is the part that
becomes quickly memory bound,
and this is why
inference is hard.
And so there's many things you
can do to speed up inference.
You can try to use a cheaper
model by pruning a larger model
or you can quantize,
you can distill.
You can use this technique
called speculative decoding,
where you use a cheaper
model to run ahead and guess
a bunch of tokens.
And now, you use the
full model, which
can operate on those tokens in
parallel to see if it's good.
And if you got lucky, then you
can accept all those tokens
and you're much
faster than if you're
doing one token at a time.
And of course, you can
do systems optimizations.
There's a bunch of kernels
that are designed specifically
for inference.
And then one of the interesting
things about inference
is that, if you're
running a service,
queries are coming at you at
potentially different times,
and then you have to figure
out how to batch them up.
Whereas in training,
you basically
already define your
batches and everything
is much more predictable.
So in Assignment
2, there's going
to be implementing
kernels in Triton
and doing some of
parallel training.
The details here
might actually change.
As the CAAs have grand plans
for revamping the systems.
So the assignment
might look a bit
different from last
year's, but it will cover
roughly the same material.
One thing I will mention is that
there's this wonderful book out
of some Google people called
How to Scale Your Model,
and I think it's really
nice for providing
a conceptual understanding
of roofline analysis,
and transformer math, and
doing LLMs conceptually.
So I highly recommend
you take a look at that.
Now, the only thing is that it's
from Google, so it's about TPUs.
But a lot of the high
level concepts are similar.
And now, they have a new chapter
on how to think about GPUs.
OK.
So the third assignment
is about scaling laws.
So by now, you've
trained a language model.
You can make it go really
fast by optimizing kernels
in parallel.
Now, you want to scale up.
So how do you scale up?
So imagine the
following setting.
If you had 1e25 FLOPs, so this
is tens of millions of dollars
of compute, what
model would you train?
So this is, I think,
a daunting task
because if you mess up,
well, that's a lot of money
down the drain.
And you can't do your,
probably, typical hyperparameter
tuning at that scale because
you only get to train one model.
And so this is the
key problem that you
have to deal with in large
language model training
that you don't have to really
deal with if you're just fine
tuning a model or doing
small scale stuff.
And so the key
conceptual shift here
is that we shouldn't
think about a single model
that we're training, but really
think about a scaling recipe.
And a scaling recipe is a
mapping from a FLOP budget,
let's say 1e25 or 1e24, to
a set of hyperparameters.
Basically a config file.
And for a given scaling
recipe, what we will do
is run a bunch of experiments
to compute the loss that you
get at smaller scales, and
then you fit a scaling law,
and that enables you to predict
the loss at a target scale.
So maybe you run some
small experiments,
you fit a scaling law,
and then you predict out
what you're going to
get at a larger scale.
So that's the primitive.
Now using this, what
you can do is now
you can optimize
the scaling recipe,
targeting a larger scale using
smaller scale experiments, which
is wonderful.
And second of all, you
can predict the loss
that you're going to, in
theory, achieve before actually
running the experiment.
Which allows you
to go raise money.
And you say, well, look, I ran
the small scale experiments,
and I think I can get really--
like, a GPD-5 level model.
Please give me a lot of money
so I can train that model.
But one thing I think is
maybe another misconception
is that scaling laws
are not laws of nature.
They don't just
happen automatically.
You have to will
them into existence.
And this happens by
careful construction
of a scaling recipe.
And the scaling recipe,
remember, it has to extrapolate.
So what this typically
means is that you
have a sequence of
hyperparameters which,
say, as the scale increases,
maybe the learning rate
is a constant, maybe it
drops, maybe the batch size
increases by how much.
And these are things
that a scaling
recipe has to figure out.
And so you parameterize.
So then in order to get these
predictable scaling laws,
one thing that you actually
have to think about
is how do you
parameterize the model
in a way to get what's called
hyperparameter transfer?
Meaning that the hyperparameters
you use at small scale
are either the ones that
you use at larger scale
or are predictable
functions of it.
Because if every scale, your
learning rate is sometimes 1e-5,
and sometimes 1e-4, then
you're not going to be able
to magically guess the right
learning rate when you are
at larger scale.
So one shift in thinking is
that predictability is actually
at least as important
as optimality.
So you normally think,
oh, we're trying
to optimize for
efficiency here, and we
want to hyperparameter tune
and make things optimal.
And yes, you do want to
do that, but you also
want this predictability so
that you don't get surprised
at larger scale.
So this is state setting.
The actual scaling laws
we're going to look at
are fairly classic.
So these are-- some of you might
have seen this idea of, well,
if I give you a FLOPs
budget, should you train--
how should you balance training
a larger model versus training
on more tokens?
And this is where the classic
compute optimal scaling laws
from Kaplan et Al and the
so-called Chinchilla scaling
laws comes in.
The basic idea is that
you for each FLOPs budget,
so let's say 6e18
all the way to 3e21,
you sweep across different model
sizes and you choose the best
one.
So think about
minimizing each of these.
And then you fit a curve that
allows you to, basically,
predict the number of
parameters given a FLOPs budget.
And if you're lucky, it will
rely roughly on the line.
And if you're
unlucky, it's going
to be all over the place, which
means that you should have
no confidence that you're going
to be able to predict reliably.
And so the upshot of
this, this is quite crude,
but a rule of thumb is, the 20
times the number of parameters
is the number of data
points you should train on.
So a 70B parameter model should
be trained on roughly 1.4
trillion tokens.
Of course, depending on the
data set and architecture,
this number will actually vary.
Also, this doesn't take you
into account the inference cost.
A lot of models
these days are small,
but they're trained
on way more tokens
than is compute optimal
because you want a smaller
model for inference reasons.
So one fun thing that we've
been doing in the Marin project
is pre-registering our results.
So we fit a bunch
of scaling plots
at different compute budgets.
We fit a scaling law, and we
basically made these predictions
out to 1E22 FLOPs.
This one is actually training.
If you go to the Marin
website, you can follow along.
It should actually be done
maybe as early as tonight.
So maybe on Wednesday I'll
report back on how we did
and see how we measure--
how we match the
pre-registered loss.
So the idea here is that
we made a prediction
on if we were to train this
large model, which we've never
trained before.
If we can predict how
well it's going to do,
then that's really nice.
So in Assignment 3, I
think this is either fun
or actually, it's a fun--
let's just say it's
a fun assignment.
[LAUGHTER]
So we're going to define this
training API, which basically,
you give us hyperparameters, and
we're going to give you a loss
back.
So what we're going
to try to do is
simulate what happens if you
could do a lot of training runs.
And of course, we don't have
enough compute to actually allow
everyone to train their
own API model or anything.
So basically, we trained
a bunch of models offline,
and we, basically,
provide this cache.
So it looks like
you're training.
And what you're going to
do is submit training jobs.
You give us a config, basically,
we give you a loss back
and then you could
do whatever you want.
We would recommend you fit
scaling laws to these points.
And then you extrapolate.
And then we give you a
budget, and we basically
evaluate how well
your model landed.
So it is meant to--
I was going to say, it's meant
to replicate the high stress
scenarios if you actually had
a budget like $100 million
that you need to spend.
You have to be very careful
about how you spend this.
Of course, this is low stakes.
So at this point, you will
have, you train a model,
how to make it fast,
you know to scale up.
Now, what's missing?
What do you train the model on?
And that's going to be
the subject of the data
section, which is arguably one
of the most important things
because data quality basically
specifies how good your model is
going to be.
One way to also frame
it is, what do you
want your model to do?
Data, basically, reflects
what your model wants.
So do you want to speak
multiple languages?
Be good at having
a conversation?
Do you want to run long
agentic coding tasks?
And so part of
that is also going
to-- so we're going to start by
talking about evaluation, which,
basically, defines the
capabilities that you'd
like your model to have.
One thing we'll talk
about is, evaluation
is a fairly deep topic.
It's not just about
running on some benchmarks.
There are internal evaluation
metrics for model development.
And what matters here is that
smoothness across scales so
that there-- remember, we
want things to be predictable.
Relative performance matters.
You don't care,
necessarily, how well
this does in absolute
terms, because, let's say,
a perplexity number
is just like, what
is a perplexity of 1.2 on some
held out data really mean?
And then there's
external metrics.
These are things that you
report to your customers
or your reviewers or whoever
you're presenting your thing to.
And here, ecological
validity really matters.
And I think sometimes these
two things get conflated,
but I think they really
serve two distinct purposes.
And so you can think
about perplexity
as something that
is really helpful
for internal development.
And still to this
day, perplexity
is a very good way of capturing
the intrinsic quality of a model
without getting--
worrying about benchmarking.
Now, there's a separate question
of what you run your evals on.
And the recommended
thing is, well,
if you have some data that's
not in the internet, that
would be good because you
can avoid contamination.
OK.
So and then there's
advanced use cases
which are more representative
of external facing use cases.
So one thing to also note
is that language models
are purportedly very
general purpose.
So it's only fitting
that we actually
need a very diverse
set of evaluations.
And I would always recommend
having many evaluations
that look at-- you can average
them into a single number,
but often that average conflates
a lot of different things.
So now after we
set up the evals,
we know what we're building.
How do you get the data?
Well, first thing is that data
does not just fall from the sky.
It has to be actively curated.
Often, I think,
especially in classes
and also in research,
sometimes you're
just given a data set,
and then it's like,
OK, well, now, I do
stuff on the data set.
But a lot of language
models, especially
if you want to collect
these large data sets,
you have to go and
actively look at it.
So web pages are crawled
from the internet.
There's books, I guess, which
is controversial at this point,
but arXiv papers,
GitHub code, and so on.
This is an old figure
from the pile from 2021.
And you can see, language
modeling data sets
are fairly diverse.
There's, especially
these days, I
think, a lot of contention
around, is it fair use
to train on copyrighted data?
Maybe sometimes you have
to license data and so on.
So there's legal issues
around data which, I think,
are quite important.
For example, a lot of GitHub
code doesn't have a license.
So how do you interpret that?
Do you assume it's permissive,
or do you be conservative
and assume it's not permissive?
So there's also-- the fact is
that data is not even text.
It's either HTML or PDFs,
or a code is directories.
And this requires processing
to turn it into actual text
to be usable for training.
So that's the topic
of data processing.
There's a few steps
that has to happen here.
Transformation, converting
some nontexting in a text.
Filtering, keeping
only the good stuff.
If the random internet document
in Common Crawl is extremely bad
and you don't want to
train on it, most likely.
You want to deduplicate.
There's multiple
sources, or how do you
combine the different sources?
And then finally, more recently,
there's been a lot of work
on generating
synthetic data, which
could mean taking the real
data and just rewriting it
into things that are more the
downstream task or just more
Wikipedia like, or
whatever you want.
So this is an active
area of research.
Also, data can be used
both for pretraining.
Something called
mid training, which
is usually the high
quality data that you
put at the end of
the pretraining step.
And this includes
long context data
such as maybe BigCode
repositories or books.
And then finally, there's
post-training data,
which are maybe conversations
or agentic traces with tool
calling.
So in Assignment 4,
we're going to make
you start with a very raw
corpus, like a rock web crawl,
and do all the work to
filter and to dedupe,
and make the data clean.
So this is, I would say--
I don't know if I would call it
not fun, but it is certainly,
I think, a lot of what
people would call dirty work.
But that is, I think,
an important part
of building a language model
from scratch so you have
to get the full experience.
So finally, alignment.
So far we've, basically, trained
a model using full supervision.
Predict the next token
or the next few tokens.
Now at this point, the model
should already be reasonable,
but we can improve it further
by using weak supervision.
And why weak supervision?
It's because sometimes
it's easier to critique
than it is to generate.
So you can't always
have data that says,
this is the right
response to this prompt,
but maybe you can have a way of
specifying what good looks like.
So then, the basic template
is that you generate responses
from the model.
You score them either with a
human or verify or a LM judge,
and then you update the model
to prefer better responses.
This can be instantiated either
through various RL algorithms
such as PPO or GRPO, or in a
simpler, for preference data,
DPO.
So the challenges around
RL are that RL algorithms
are unstable and hard to tune.
Some of you probably know this
from firsthand experience.
Personally, I prefer to keep
things as much in the fold
so we supervise the case
as long as possible.
And then finally, OK,
fine, I have to do RL.
But some people, for whatever
reason, like doing RL.
Also, what we'll,
hopefully, talk
about this year is that
if you do RL at scale
and try to maximize
your throughput,
there's actually a lot
of systems challenges.
You have to have an inference
server and a training server.
And then the inference server
has to generate these rollouts.
Especially if you do
RL against environments
that involve code execution.
It's a whole kind of
orchestration game.
And then if your workers
lag behind or then
you get into off policy
issues, and then you're
constantly kind of juggling
this on-policyness with a desire
to maximize throughput.
It's a big, wonderful
mess, which, hopefully,
we'll talk more about
when we come to that.
So Assignment 5,
we're still deciding
what exactly we want to do.
Last year, it was
implemented DPO and GRPO,
and get it working for
some math benchmark,
but we'll see how
much farther we
can push it on the realistic
dimension this year.
So again, remember
it's about efficiency.
And efficiency can be
either data efficiency
or compute efficiency.
So the way to think about it,
you have all these resources.
you have data, you
have the hardware,
which has compute cores, you
have memory, communication
bandwidth.
And you're just
trying to figure out
how do you build the best model
according to some evaluation
given a fixed set of resources.
So through this
lens, I think, you
can actually think about a
lot of these design decisions
as optimizing for this.
So systems, clearly, that's
about compute efficiency.
Tokenization, as I mentioned
before, you can't just
work with raw bytes,
but that's going
to be very compute inefficient,
at least with today's model
architectures.
And so a lot of tokenization
is about improving
compute efficiency.
Model architecture, many of
the changes that we'll see
are motivated by reducing
the memory or flops.
In fact, a lot of them
are influenced by the need
to have faster inference.
Data filtering, you
can also view as--
through efficiency lens.
We don't want to waste
time updating gradients
on a bunch of
redundant bad data,
even if it might not hurt you,
but it hurts you in the sense
that if you have a fixed compute
budget, more time on bad data
means less time on good data.
And then finally, scaling
laws is explicitly
about how you can, essentially,
do effective hyperparameter
tuning on much smaller models.
And now tomorrow, we might
become data-constrained,
and the calculus of what design
decisions you should take
might change.
But I think the
overall mindset which
we're trying to
teach you is think
about the efficiency
of your approach.
OK, let me stop there.
Are there any
questions about any
of these assignments or topics?
OK.
So now let's do tokenization.
So this is-- we're jumping
into our first unit here.
So Andrej Karpathy has
this really good video
on tokenization.
You should check it out.
So starting point is raw
text is what is text?
It's Unicode strings.
And on the other hand,
the language model
places a distribution
over sequences of tokens
usually represented as indices.
So we need a procedure
that encodes these strings
into tokens, and also a
procedure that decodes
tokens back into strings.
So a tokenizer is
basically something
that can do this round trip.
So here are some
examples to give you
a flavor for how
tokenizers work.
Actually, I should have tried
to get in there earlier.
So this is not going to work.
If you go to the site
you can play around
with different tokenizers.
So some observations here.
And you'll appreciate why
tokenizers are kind of annoying
and why people want
to get rid of them.
So a word and its--
a word conglomerate
with its preceding space
are different tokens.
So many tokens you'll
actually see are space a word,
which is fine, but
kind of strange.
So this hello and
this hello is actually
two completely different
indices that have nothing
to do with each other.
And sometimes, depending
on the tokenizer you use,
numbers are represented with--
every few digits is a token.
Sometimes, it's predictable,
and sometimes, it's not.
Some tokenizers try to
make every digit a token,
but then you're blowing up
the number of tokens you have.
So there's some trade off there.
So here's the GPT-5 tokenizer.
So you can take this string and
convert it into these indices.
And then you can decode
it back into the string.
And so tokenizers
should round trip.
If you implement tokenizer,
it doesn't round trip,
you have a problem.
So the compression ratio here is
the number of bytes per token.
So in this case, we have, the
number of bytes of this string
is 20.
The number of tokens is 8.
And you do 20 divided by 8.
So the compression ratio is 2.5.
OK, so 2.5 bytes per token.
The larger the
compression ratio,
that means the shorter
the sentence, which
is good because
attention is quadratic,
and you want to make sure
the sent sequence is shorter.
Now, you could obviously
increase the compression ratio
by increasing the vocab
size, but then, you
get into sparsity
where more and more--
because every element
of vocab is treated
like a distinct element.
So these days, tokenizers,
especially multilingual
tokenizers, have 100k or
200k tokens, distinct tokens.
So you can look at the
GPD token vocabulary.
I think we'll skip it
in the interest of time.
So how do you build a tokenizer?
So I'm going to go
through this fast.
So the first thing
you might do is
like, well, Unicode
string, that's
a sequence of
Unicode characters.
And each character
is an integer,
which you can call
ord in Python,
and you get some number out.
And this can be converted
into characters.
So let's just build a
character level tokenizer which
basically breaks
up each character
and encodes it in a token.
And then this can decode back.
Life is good.
So now, there are 150k
Unicode characters.
So your vocab size could
be 150k, which is a lot.
I mean, it's not
crazy, but I think
the bigger problem is that many
characters are actually rare,
which means that it's really an
inefficient use of a vocabulary.
And also, the compression
ratio, which reflects this
is not that great.
So most of the time, you're
actually using a lot of tokens
to represent your sequence.
And many of the indices are
actually not being very used.
So this is not a
very good tokenizer.
So here's another attempt.
So you can turn
strings into bytes.
So Unicode has a UTF-8 encoding,
which means that you can--
sometimes a string like "a"
is just 1 byte, and sometimes,
a string is multiple bytes.
So let's build a
tokenizer around that.
So we can take this
string and convert it
into a sequence of bytes.
And notice that this is
a longer sequence now,
but all the numbers
are between 0 and 255,
because that's
what a byte means.
And the compression ratio
is 1, which is not great.
So byte sequences
can be very long,
but the vocab size is small.
OK.
So both of these are really bad.
So let's try to
make some progress.
So this is what actually
people used to do in NLP,
if people remember.
So if you take a string, I
can just chunk it up into--
break it up by spaces or
some regular expression.
And let's just call each
of these chunks a token.
So what is good about this one
is that each token is meaningful
because humans invented
words, and words
tend to have a stable
semantic meaning.
But your vocab
size is the number
of distinct chunks
in the training
data, which could be a lot.
And also, your compression
ratio, I mean, it's quite good,
but the vocabulary can be huge.
Actually, it's worse than that
because though the vocabulary
could be actually
unbounded, right?
Because at test time, you
might get some sequence
and you tokenize, and
then you have a token
you've never seen before.
And people used to
assign these UNK token,
but that's really
ugly and can mess up
your perplexity calculations.
So this is also not great.
OK, so what we're
actually going to do
is called byte pair encoding.
And this was introduced a long
time ago for data compression.
Way before language models were
really on the scene, really.
It was first introduced to
NLP for doing neural machine
translation.
And the first paper that
used BPE for LLMs was GPT-2.
So the basic idea
is that you're going
to train the
tokenizer on raw text
to construct a vocabulary
that's tailored to the data.
And you're also going to have
this property that everything
becomes-- can be tokenized.
If it's rare, then it just
breaks up into smaller units
rather than having
this UNK token.
So common sequences are going
to be represented as one token.
Rare sequences are going to
be split into multiple tokens.
That's the idea.
So the algorithm is fairly
simple, conceptually.
So you start, basically,
with your corpus.
Let's assume it's
one long sequence.
You get a byte sequence.
Each byte starts as a token.
And then we're going to
merge successive pairs
of adjacent tokens that
occur the most frequently.
So let's step through how
this is going to work in code.
So here's a simple string,
"the cat in the hat,"
and here's the implementation
of the BPE algorithm.
So we're going to turn that
into a sequence of bytes.
And then we're going to--
first, we're going
to, basically, count
the number of times
successive tokens appear.
So 116, 104 shows up
twice, so we get this.
And then we're going to
find the pair that happens
the most number of times.
So that's 116, 104.
I guess there's a few ties, but
we'll just take the first one.
And then we're going
to merge that pair.
And by merging that pair what
we do is we create a new token.
In this case, this is going
to be called token 256.
It's going to
represent this pair,
and we're going to add
it to our vocabulary.
So 256 is going to represent
the sequence of th.
So t and h have been merged.
And we're going to call--
every time we see th,
we're going to use
256 to represent that.
And then we go through
indices, and then we
replace every occurrence
of 116, 104 with 256.
So those two places
have been replaced.
And then we iterate.
So the next time we do this,
we're going to find 256 and 101.
We're going to merge that.
And now we have 257.
And then we're going to
merge that one more time,
and we're going to get 258.
So over time, the
sequence is shrinking
and the vocabulary
size is growing.
OK.
So let me-- and the
compression ratio here is--
that we get for this, I
mean, this toy example is 1.5
OK.
So now that you
have a tokenizer,
how do you tokenize new text?
Well, you take a new
string and you encode it.
And conceptually, what
happens is that you basically
go through the set of
merges that you've made,
and then you just apply
the merges to your string.
OK, let me actually not
step through that code.
So that will give
you a sequence.
So this is a sequence encoding
of "the quick brown fox."
And then when you decode it,
you get the same thing back.
So I went through
this a bit fast,
just in the interest of time.
I will say that this
implementation works.
This is a full-blown
BPE implementation.
It's extremely slow.
So in Assignment 1, we're
going to ask you to,
basically, make it faster.
So currently, encode
loops over all the merges,
which is very slow
because you might have--
the number of merges
you have is essentially
the vocab size minus 256.
So you only want to loop
over the merges that matter.
And you have to build some
indices to make that happen.
There's some details
around special tokens.
Conceptually not deep,
but important to building
a modern tokenizer.
Another thing is that I've
presented the tokenizer just
for simplicity.
As you take an entire string
and then you try to tokenize it,
really, what happens is
that you break it up into--
your text into
chunks, and then you
apply tokenizer on each chunk.
So that's going
to be much faster.
And then try to make
it as fast as possible.
At some point you might
realize that Python is just not
very fast.
And if you want to implement it
in your favorite language, Rust
or C or something,
then go for it.
OK, so quick summary.
Tokenizers convert between
strings and tokens or indices.
The previous
character-base, byte-base,
word-base are highly
suboptimal in their own way.
BPE is effective heuristic
that is data driven.
So it seems to be
pretty effective.
Now, like I said before,
maybe next year, I
don't have to teach
this, but for this year,
we're stuck with tokenization.
Even if we get rid of
tokenization though,
I think whatever solution
replaces it, I think,
has to satisfy the
following properties.
If you have the
model, the transformer
needs to operate on some sort
of abstractions of the sequence.
And this is most evident if
you think about not just text,
but video or DNA sequences where
the individual bytes or units
are actually quite
low signal to noise,
and you have to do some
sort of abstraction
to lift it into a place where
you can do modeling on that.
And then finally,
as I mentioned,
chunks should be variable.
You want adaptive computation.
Not all bytes are
treated the same.
And if you don't
do that, I think,
you're going to be suboptimal.
So any end-to-end
solution also, I think,
has to have these properties.
OK.
So with that, I will end.
Next time, on
Wednesday, we're going
to start the unit on
resource accounting.
Which is sort of a baby
system, I would say.
And then after that, we're going
to go back into architectures
and go from there.
All right.